In this lesson we're going to get the
このレッスンでは、カメラを移動したり
camera moving and following the player.
カメラにプレイヤーを追わせたりします
Currently the camera is stationary.
現在、カメラは固定されています
We need to tie the camera to
Camera を Player ゲームオブジェクトに
the Player game object.
連携させる必要があります
We can do this by making our camera
それを行うには
a child of the Player game object.
Camera を Player ゲームオブジェクトの子にします
Drag the Camera in the hierarchy
Hierarchy の Camera を
on to the Player.
Player の上にドラッグします
In simply terms we can think of the parent/child
簡単に言えば、親子関係は
relationship as attaching the child to the parent
一方通行の関係で、子を親に
in a one way connection.
連携させていると考えられます
If the parent moves the child will move
もし親が動くと、子も動き
and maintain it's relationship to the parent.
親に対する関係を維持します
If the child moves however the
一方、子が動いても
parent will not be moved.
親は動きません
This is a fairly typical setup with the
Camera を Player の子にするのは
camera as a child of the Player.
かなり典型的な設定です
If we move the Player in the editor
プレイヤーをエディターで動かすと
we can see that the camera's field of view
グレイの枠で示されたカメラの視界が
represented by the grey box,
プレイヤーとともに動くのが
moves with it.
わかります
If we change the Player's rotation the
プレイヤーの Rotation の値を変えると
camera rotates as well.
カメラも回転します
Let's test this in play mode.
プレイモードでテストしてみましょう
We enter play mode and use the
プレイモードにし
arrow keys to move.
再生を押すと動きます
But when we hit the wall the UFO
UFO が壁にぶつかると
begins to spin and things go a little crazy.
スピンを始め、妙な状態になります
What's happening here?
何が起こったのでしょうか
Well, with the camera as a child of the player,
Camera は Player の子なので
even though the camera is not moving at all
カメラそのものは動いていなくても
relative to the Player's game object.
プレイヤーのゲームオブジェクトと連動します
The Player's game object is rotating
プレイヤーのゲームオブジェクトが回転すると
so the camera's point of view rotates with it.
カメラの視点もそれと一緒に回転します
This may make us, or our audience, queazy.
これでは、私たちも、オーディエンスも疲れてしまいます
This is clearly not an ideal
この設定は、このゲームには
setup for this particular game.
適切でないのは明らかです
In a typical setup the camera,
一般的な設定で、Camera は
as a child of the Player game object,
Player ゲームオブジェクトの子として
will always be in a position
常にその直接の親に対して
relative to it's immediate parent,
相対的な位置をとっています
and this position will be the parent's
そして、この位置は
position in the game,
ゲーム内での親の位置であり
modified or offset by any
子の Transform の値に
values in the child's transform.
修正やオフセットを行います
In our case we can't have the camera
ここでは
as a child of the Player,
Camera を Player の子にすべきではないので
so let's detach it by dragging it
Hierarchy で Camera をPlayer の上にドラッグして
above the Player in the hierarchy.
切り離します
Our offset value will
私たちが使うオフセット値は
be the difference between the Player game object
Player ゲームオブジェクトと camera の
and the camera.
差です
Now we need to associate
ここでは、子としてではなくスクリプトで
the camera with the Player game object
Camera をPlayer ゲームオブジェクトに
not as a child but with a script.
関連づける必要があります
With the main camera still highlighted
Main camera をハイライトしたままで
let's use the Add Component button
Add Component ボタンを使って
to add a new script.
新しいスクリプトを加え
And let's name the script CameraController.
スクリプト名を CameraController としましょう
If we type the name of a component in
検索フィールドにコンポーネント名を入れ
the search box and it's not found
見つからないときは
it will prompt us with the New Script button.
New Script ボタンが表示されます
This is a shortcut which allows us to
これでスクリプトを手早く作成できます
quickly create scripts by typing their name
名前を入力して
and clicking New Script.
New Script ボタンをクリックするだけです
Click Create and Add,
Create and Add をクリックするか
or simply the return
エンターキーを押して
or enter key to confirm our selection.
選択を確定します
As we saw earlier,
以前にも見たように
this way of creating a script will create
このようにスクリプトを作成すると
that script asset on the root
Project ビューのルートか
or top level of our project view.
最上レベルに作成されます
Let's put CameraController in the
CameraController を
Scripts folder and then
Script フォルダーに入れてから
open it for editing.
開いて編集しましょう
We need two variables here.
ここでは、2 つの変数が必要です
A public game object reference to the Player,
Player を参照するパブリックなゲームオブジェクトと
and a private vector3
オフセット値を記憶する
to hold our offset value.
プライベートの vector3 です
Type public GameObject player.
public GameObject player と入力します
Then type private vector3 offset.
次に private vector3 offset
Offset is private because
Offset はプライベートです
we can set that value here
なぜなら、このスクリプト内で
in the script.
値を設定するからです
For our offset value we will
オフセット値は
take the current transform position
Camera の現在のTransform 位置から
of the camera and
Player の Transform 位置を
subtract the transform position
差し引き
of the Player to find
2 者の違いを
the difference between the two.
求めます
This will be the offset value.
これがoffset 値になります
So in Start we can make
それでまず offset を
offset equal to our
Transform 位置から
transform position
Player の Transform 位置を
minus the Player's transform position.
差し引いた値にします
Type offset = transform.position - player.transform.position
Type offset = transform.position - player.transform.position　と入力します
When written like this
このように入力するとき
transform references the transform
この transform はスクリプトが
of the game object that this
アタッチされているゲームオブジェクトの
script is attached to.
Transform を参照しています
It's worth noting that as this
覚えておくといいのは
script is attached to the same game object
このスクリプトが camera コンポーネントと同じゲームオブジェクトに
as the camera component
アタッチされているということです
transform.position references the
このスクリプトと camera コンポーネントは
transform's position for the camera
同じオブジェクトにアタッチされているので
as they are both attached
transform.position は
to the same game object.
Camera の Transform の位置を参照します
In Update we'll set the
Update で、
transform position of our camera
Camera のTransform 位置を
to our Player's transform position
Player の Transform 位置プラス
plus the offset.
Offset に設定します
This will happen every frame
Update 内に置くため
because it's in Update.
これはすべてのフレームで起こります
Type transform.position = player.transform.position + offset
transform.position = player.transform.position + offset　と入力します
This means as we move our
つまり、キーボードで制御して
Player with the controls on the keyboard
Player を移動するので
that each frame before
各フレームで、カメラに写るものを
displaying what the camera can see
表示する前に
the camera is moved in to a
カメラはまるでそのオブジェクトの子であるかのように
new position align with the Player object,
プレイヤーと並んで
just as if it were a child of that
新しい位置へ移動します
object except that it will not
ただし、ゲームボードの周りを
be spinning around the game board
親オブジェクトがするように
as the parent object spins.
スピンしたりはしませんが
However, Update is not the best place for this code.
ただし、Update はこのコードに最適ではありません
It is true that Update runs
確かに Update は
every frame and in Update
すべてのフレームで実行されるため
each frame we can track the
Update でPlayer の
position of the Player's game object
ゲームオブジェクトの位置を追跡し
and set the position of the camera.
カメラの位置を設定できます
However for follow cameras,
ただし、フォローパン、
procedural animation and gathering last known states
プロシージャルアニメーション、最終ステートの取得には
it's best to use LateUpdate.
LateUpdate が最適です
Let's change Update to LateUpdate.
Update を LateUpdate に変えてみましょう
LateUpdate runs every frame,
LateUpdate はUpdate と同じように
just like Update, but it is
すべてのフレームで実行されますが、
guaranteed to run after all
Update ですべてが処理された後に
items have been processed in Update.
はじめて実行されます
So when we set the position of the camera
そのため、カメラの位置を設定するときに
we know absolutely that the Player
確実にPlayer はそのフレームで
has already moved for that frame.
すでに作動しています。
So let's test this, let's save our scene
では、テストしてみましょう。スクリプトを保存して
and return to Unity.
Unity に戻ります
First we need to create a reference
最初にPlayer ゲームオブジェクトへの参照を
to the Player game object by
作成する必要があります
dragging the Player game object
Player ゲームオブジェクトをドラッグして
on to the Player slot
CameraController コンポーネントの
in the CameraController's component.
Player スロットに移動します
Enter play mode.
プレイモードにします
And now we get the behaviour we want.
思った通りのビヘイビアになりました
The camera follows the UFO,
カメラは、衝突しても
without rotating when we collide.
スピンすることなく UFO を追います
In the next assignment we'll finish the
次回は、このゲームのアイテムを
basic play area by creating
作成し配置して
and placing our special pickup objects.
基本のプレイエリアを終了させます